Hello
Speaker 1: friends. So AOC is out on the warpath defending her belief that the Trump administration is presiding over a system of concentration camps in
the United
Speaker 1: States. She identifies them as existing on the southern border, but presumably they could be elsewhere because she's saying that immigration detention centers
Speaker 1: should now be regarded as concentration camps, and those centers are all over the country, not just in the southern border area. So, there are a couple things to sort of unpack here. Number one, if you're going to invoke the term concentration camp, at least per the parlance of American political dialogue,
you
Speaker 1: are just necessarily invoking the legacy of the Holocaust, okay?
Most people
Speaker 1: grow up learning about the Holocaust, and one of the central features of the Holocaust was concentration camps. Later, yes, death camps. But the implication there
Speaker 2: is really hard to deny,
right?
Speaker 2: If you want to address a phenomenon without being evocative of the Holocaust, probably what you do is use a term other than concentration camps. So, if that's not what she's intending to do, then you have to question what exactly is her intention.
This
Speaker 2: should be separated from the substance of whatever problems
Speaker 1: there legitimately are in the immigration system. There is a serious influx of migrants coming from the South, largely due to instability and destitution and severe hardship in Central America, whether it be Honduras, Guatemala, etc. So that's a real thing. And the conditions in which those individuals
Speaker 2: are housed...
Speaker 2: is a subject of legitimate scrutiny, but can we best rationally address those problems by invoking the specter of the Holocaust? I think that is highly debatable and I would say no. And in fact, Bernie Sanders, when asked about this on CNN, also stated that he does not use the term concentration camps to describe the problems that are existent
In
Speaker 2: the area of the southern
Speaker 1: border or elsewhere having to do with the present issues involving immigration influxes.
So unless you're
Speaker 1: going to argue that Bernie Sanders is somehow denying fascism or is enabling these Nazi-like abuses, then...
I
Speaker 1: think you have to at least concede that there are real problems in terms of the nomenclature being invoked by somebody like AOC. Okay? And
it also
Speaker 1: doesn't mean that the right-wing criticisms of her or at
least like
Speaker 1: the neoconservative criticisms of her from people like Liz Cheney aren't necessarily valid either. But these terms actually have real significance.
Speaker 2: And if you're in a position like AOC...
Speaker 2: where much of what you do involves political communication, then you can't act surprised or indignant when people take your rhetoric seriously.
And here's an
Speaker 2: issue that I have in particular. AOC distributed
Speaker 1: an article that she claimed justified her use of the term concentration camp. And yeah, concentration camps...
Speaker 1: technically exist outside the context of the Nazi Holocaust. But
when you
Speaker 1: invoke it kind of casually, just in an American political context, the Holocaust is what immediately comes to mind for most people
who hear
Speaker 1: that term being espoused. But anyway, AOC put out this article that she says justifies her use of the term.
And in that article, it explicitly says,
Speaker 2: Elaborates that the network of immigration detention centers that AOC is now characterizing as concentration camps have existed for decades.
They were more
Speaker 2: or less initiated in the 90s under Bill Clinton, and
they
Speaker 1: were bolstered in subsequent administrations under Bush, under Obama, and now to a different degree under Trump.
Speaker 1: Trump you can kind of quibble along the margins with which administration did exactly what in terms of Building up
Speaker 2: or expanding this system of detention centers, but the fact remains according to the article that AOC herself promulgated that this system has been in existence for decades. So
the question I would have to AOC then is Are
Speaker 2: you claiming?
Speaker 2: that Bill Clinton and Barack Obama presided over a system of concentration camps and that everybody kind of looked the other way or didn't pay much attention just because they liked the current president or
the president
Speaker 2: who was at that time in office?
Because if
Speaker 2: so, what does that say about our country? Or are you suggesting that Trump has unique qualities which now made...
Speaker 2: These immigration centers rightly characterized as concentration camps. When did they transform into something that was sort of run-of-the-mill, maybe had a lot of problems and abuses, but was kind of the ordinary machinery of the American state? When did they transform into something as incredibly egregious and disturbing and existentially threatening as concentration camps?
Was
Speaker 2: it January 20th, 2017 by any chance? Because if so, that's really arbitrary. And that suggests that you are basing your rhetoric not on the substance of how these places are actually operated, but on who the figurehead is at the top.
And that would
Speaker 2: suggest that your rhetoric actually is quite hollow and superficial and overly moralistic and intended to get a rise out of people emotionally and.
Speaker 2: And that I just have to object to on the merits. Now, if you're going to say that you believe that they've been concentration camps all along, okay, at least that's a consistent view. It still seems quite hyperbolic, but
if you're
Speaker 2: going to argue that something just magically shifted overnight when Trump assumed office, that doesn't make sense either, because
the
Speaker 2: look at some of this stuff that happened under Obama that, at least according to the criteria that people
are now
Speaker 2: alleging constitutes a concentration camp,
the abuses that
Speaker 2: occurred under Obama
would have
Speaker 2: been easily the same. So this person, Andy Grewal, who is a professor of law at the University of Iowa, actually had a good thread today
Speaker 2: Which basically asked,
when did
Speaker 2: the label concentration camp spring into existence?
Similar as I
Speaker 2: question, did it happen to be on January 20th, 2017? Because if so, that's extremely arbitrary and actually reductive and insulting. So
for example, Greenwald notes that
Speaker 1: the Obama administration argued successfully in
Speaker 2: 2016 that it could separate parents from their children
immediately.
in a
Speaker 2: Ninth Circuit case called Flores v. Lynch, okay?
So
Speaker 1: if you're ground for asserting that what's going on now, or what's gone on under Trump is the so-called family separation policy,
then
Speaker 2: that's not a sufficient ground because it occurred under Obama, maybe in different manifestations, but it occurred
Speaker 1: to some extent under the previous administration.
Also
Speaker 1: under Obama, Grewal notes, children were kept in cages so crowded they were, quote, forced to sleep standing up or not at all. So they had
Speaker 2: overcrowded conditions in Obama, in the Obama administration. And the ACLU put out a study of these immigration centers under Obama and concluded that they showed poverty.
Speaker 2: pervasive abuse and neglect, I'm quoting,
of unaccompanied
Speaker 2: immigrant children detained by U.S. Customs and Border Protection.
Okay, so
Speaker 2: I'm not just making a cheap, oh, but Obama did it point here. I'm saying that you have to have a consistent standard for when something magically becomes a concentration camp.
And if it
Speaker 2: wasn't a concentration camp under your lights, under Obama, you have to explain why, and you can't ignore what happened in the very recent...
Speaker 2: past. We're not talking about decades and decades ago. We're talking about 2015. All right. So
what's the story
Speaker 2: there? Because if you
don't have a
Speaker 2: compelling explanation for the logical discrepancy, the reasonable inference is that you're just using this overheated rhetoric to almost fearmonger, to inflate a threat, to...
Speaker 2: Draw on the emotional impulses of the people who you are trying to egg on politically.
Speaker 1: And that's just not responsible rhetoric on the part of a politician. And sure, other politicians do it. AOC wouldn't be alone by any
Speaker 2: stretch.
But it still is worth criticizing. And it's not to say
Speaker 2: that the Holocaust is like,
has these
Speaker 1: supernatural qualities. I mean, there's always been a running debate in Holocaust
Speaker 1: interpretive kind of modes
dating
Speaker 2: back to when it occurred about whether the Holocaust was a unique event that stands alone historically or
Speaker 1: whether it
could be
Speaker 1: properly analogized to other historical events past and present.
And I'm
Speaker 1: not coming down one way or another on that debate. I'm simply stating that
that
Speaker 1: I think it should be obvious that if you're going to invoke the Holocaust, you better have your ducks in a row, argumentatively, and it doesn't seem like AOC does. And
she should
Speaker 1: be held to a high standard because she has a ton of influence. She can single-handedly drive news cycles. She has, perhaps other than Trump, the most powerful social media
Speaker 2: platform of any politician in the U.S. So therefore, she has to, I mean, her
words...
have
Speaker 2: to be analyzed. I think some of the obsession with her, especially on the part of the
Speaker 1: right, is
excessive. But
Speaker 1: nonetheless, this is the role she's in. And on top of everything else,
using this
Speaker 2: kind of histrionic rhetoric, I think, distracts from actually
forging a
Speaker 2: rational inquiry of the real problems that exist,
And just
Speaker 2: gets everyone into this very hysterical mode where they're claiming that everything going on right now in contemporary modern day America
is just
Speaker 2: the same or is even meaningfully analogous to Germany in the late 1930s. It's just not true and it's a distraction to engage on that level.
We
Speaker 2: need to have a mental and political framework where we can engage with the real problems that do exist without necessarily resorting to these kinds of overheated and inaccurate historical comparisons that serve no purpose other than to gin up emotional
Speaker 1: reactivity.
And that,
Speaker 1: unfortunately, I think is what AOC did. And Bernie...
Speaker 1: Seems to agree because he explicitly stated that he does not use that terminology. So that
is my
Speaker 1: little input on this situation for now. I always forget to mention this, but please consider giving on Patreon, Bitcoin, PayPal. All that information is on the description box. Subscribe on YouTube here. Please subscribe to the podcast on iTunes and Stitcher. I'm going to put out a new episode of the podcast that's going to be good either tonight or tomorrow morning. So be on the lookout for that, and I will talk to you later.